Okay, the next section of your text deals with the vagina.
Recall that the vagina is a fibromuscular canal that leads to the cervix,
and the first of the disorders that we want to talk about is adenosis.
However, before we can understand adenosis, we need a little bit of background,
and so I'm going to take you to the whiteboard.
Again, the vagina is a fibromuscular canal,
and this fibromuscular canal is lined by surface epithelium,
and it so happens that the surface epithelium of this canal
is stratified squamous epithelium that is non-keratinizing.
And so what I'm drawing here, each of these boxes represents a squamous cell
that together is forming this stratified squamous epithelium
that, again, is non-keratinizing.
Now, this is the normal lining of the vaginal canal.
However, if we go back to embryology,
recall that the vaginal canal is actually derived from two different things.
The lower one-third of the vaginal canal
is derived from something called the urogenital sinus,
and the upper two-thirds of the vaginal canal
is derived from something called the malarian duct.
Now, remember that the malarian duct
is the source of the female reproductive system.
So, for example, the uterus is derived from the malarian duct,
the tubes are derived from the malarian duct,
the cervix is derived from the malarian duct,
and the upper two-thirds of the vagina
is also derived from the malarian duct.
Now, let's go back down to this lower one-third urogenital sinus.
The cells that line the urogenital sinus are normally stratified squamous epithelium.
However, the cells that line the upper two-thirds that was derived from the malarian duct in utero is columnar.
And so what happens during development is that the stratified squamous epithelium from the lower one-third
begins to extend during development again, all the way up to eventually replace the entire vaginal canal
so that these columnar cells should disappear and be replaced by squamous cells.
If there is a disruption of this process and the columnar cells persist,
then the presence of persistent columnar epithelium in the vaginal canal is called adenosis.
And that's what I've mentioned here in your text.
So adenosis is focal persistence of columnar epithelium in the upper vagina
because, of course, the upper vagina is derived from the malarian duct.
Now, this can rarely happen in a normal individual.
However, the key association is that adenosis is seen with increased incidence in females
that are exposed to a drug called DES in utero,
or females that were, I should say, exposed to a drug called DES in utero.
Now, DES, we need a little bit of a pharmacology tie-in here.
So DES actually stands for diethylstilbestarol,
and it is an estrogen-like compound that was developed in the late 1930s.
It was initially used to treat symptoms of postmenopause,
but over time it gained popularity for prevention of pregnancy-related complications.
So, for example, women who had miscarriage or who had preterm labor
would be given this drug while they were pregnant.
Eventually, we learned that this drug crossed the placenta,
and when it crossed the placenta, it would cause disruption of uterine development,
and one of the things that it would disrupt was a conversion of columnar epithelium
to squamous epithelium in the vaginal canal.
So again, remember that the lower one-third, which was derived from the urogenital sinus, was squamous,
and the upper two-thirds, which was derived from the malarian duct, was columnar.
And these squamous cells would go up and would normally replace the columnar cells.
However, DES would block this process,
and women who were exposed to DES in utero when this process was occurring in fetal life
would eventually not have this process occur properly,
and so they would have residual columnar cells,
and the presence of those residual columnar cells was called adenosis.
Here's an example of a patient with adenosis.
Essentially, I'm drawing the basement membrane here,
and everything to the left of this basement membrane is stratified squamous epithelium,
and here represents the canal.
So essentially, everything to the left is normal.
Now, in this particular woman, as the squamous cells came up and replaced,
the other thing that should have happened is that the columnar cells
that were present deep underneath the epithelium, within the canal itself,
should also have been resorbed.
And in this particular case, which these cells again here that I'm circling should have been resorbed.
However, in this particular case, these cells are not resorbed,
and so you have persistence of columnar epithelium in the upper two-thirds of the vaginal canal.
Now, you wouldn't know that this is the upper two-thirds.
I'd have to tell you that.
But in the upper two-thirds of the vaginal canal,
and so it's this persistence of columnar epithelium that again refers to adenosis,
and this picture is actually taken from a woman who was exposed to DES in utero.
Now, adenosis wouldn't be that big of an issue,
but the key problem is that adenosis can lead to another complication,
which is called clear-cell adenocarcinoma.
Carcinoma, of course, refers to a malignant proliferation of cells.
Adeno refers to the fact that those cells are forming glands,
and clear-cell tells us that they have a clear cytoplasm.
And so, essentially, the complication of adenosis is that women could develop later on in life
clear-cell adenocarcinoma.
And this is a rare complication of DES-associated vaginal adenosis.
Now, it was the discovery of clear-cell adenocarcinoma,
along with other complications that eventually led to the cessation of DES usage,
and ever since about the late 1970s, we no longer used this drug.
I'd like to briefly just talk about some of these other complications,
because it is important to know.
And so, let's just kind of review the patient populations that could be exposed to DES.
So, the first patient population that could be exposed would be a DES mom.
So, this is a mother who was pregnant, let's say, in the 60s,
and she had some preterm labor, and so she was exposed to DES.
Now, if DES mom was carrying a girl,
then the drug would cross the placenta,
and she would produce a DES daughter.
And if a DES mom was carrying a boy,
then the drug would cross the placenta,
and it would produce a DES son.
So, these are kind of the key populations that could be exposed to DES.
Now, DES daughters, the key first complication,
which we've already discussed,
is that they could get vaginal adenosis.
And the problem with adenosis is that that adenosis could potentially become
something called clear cell adenal carcinoma,
which was the feared complication of exposure to DES.
Another thing that could happen in a DES daughter
is that there could be abnormalities of just the formation of the uterus and the tubes,
in particular, the smooth muscle of the uterus and the tubes.
And so, they would get abnormalities in the formation of the uterus in relation to the tubes.
And this could lead to an increased risk of ectopic pregnancy, infertility, or pregnancy loss.
So, pregnancy and gestational type problems.
So, those are the two major complications that would arise in DES daughters.
Now, DES sons, fortunately, they have no significant complications.
Now, DES moms, the one key complication that I would point out,
is that DES moms, or mothers who were exposed to DES when they were pregnant,
have a slightly increased risk for breast carcinoma.
And that shouldn't be hard to remember,
because DES essentially was an estrogen-derived compound.
And breast carcinoma is something that is related to estrogen exposure.
And so, it's not hard to associate the exposure of an estrogen-like compound
with a cancer that's related to exposure to estrogen.
And so, those are the key patient populations that would be exposed to DES.
And those are the key complications.
And it's the learning of all of this that led to the cessation, again,
of the use of the drug, and it's no longer in use.
The second disorder that we want to talk about
is something called embrinal rhabdomyosarcoma.
Sarcoma refers to a malignant mesenchymal proliferation.
And rhabdomyo refers to a cell that has features of skeletal muscle.
And so, this is a malignant proliferation of immature skeletal muscle.
It's relatively rare.
I highly doubt you'll ever see one in your practice.
However, those things that are rare in practice are often common on exams,
and so, it's important to be aware of this disorder.
Now, this disorder has a very interesting presentation that you need to be aware of.
And that is that this disorder often presents with bleeding
and a grape-like mass, which is arising from the vagina, if it's a female,
or the penis, if it's a male.
And it classically occurs in a child less than five years of age.
Because this produces this grape-like mass,
now, it's also called sarcoma botrydes,
and botrydes refers to grape-like mass,
or it's a term that literally means grape-like mass.
Here's a picture of the grape-like mass,
and all I'm showing you here is the mass.
I'm not showing you, obviously, the protrusion of the mass
from the vagina or the penis.
But essentially, you notice all these grape-like bubbles,
or grape-like protrusions here.
And so, they call this sarcoma botrydes,
again, because of the grape-like mass,
and it also, of course, represents an embryonorhabdomyosarcoma.
Now, they don't usually show this picture on exams,
but they often show a picture of a five-year-old girl,
which is the classic picture,
and they show this mass protruding from the vagina,
and so that would be the classic presentation.
Embryonorhabdomyosarcoma has a key cell,
which forms the tumor,
and that cell is called a rhabdomyoblast.
The rhabdomyo, again, refers to skeletal muscle,
and the blast refers to the fact that it is an immature cell.
So, rhabdomyosarcoma is actually defined
by the presence of rhabdomyoblast,
and that's an important take-home here.
Now, a couple of features of the rhabdomyoblast
that we should be aware of.
The first is that rhabdomyoblast
will often show cytoplasmic cross-driation.
So, when you look at a rhabdomyoblast,
and you look at the cytoplasm,
you'll often see these cross-driations running up and down the cytoplasm,
similar to what you would see in skeletal muscle.
And so, if I were to tell you, for example,
that there is a child, and they have a tumor,
and the pathologist says that the tumor exhibits cytoplasmic cross-driations,
you're going to think about a rhabdomyoblast,
and in turn, a rhabdomyosarcoma.
Another way by which we can define the rhabdomyoblast,
or maybe I should say identify the rhabdomyoblast,
is to use something called immunohistochemistry.
Now, we can stain for certain antigens present in the cell,
which would then help us to identify the cell.
And two of the key antigens that are helpful
in identifying a rhabdomyoblast
are desmin and myogenin.
Desmin, again, is the intermediate filament
that is present in muscle cells.
And so, if we know that a cell is positive for desmin,
we know that it is a muscle cell.
And myogenin is a nuclear transcription factor
that would be present in immature skeletal muscle.
And so, if the tumor is positive for desmin and myogenin,
that would automatically tell us
that we're dealing with muscle
that is immature skeletal muscle,
and of course, because it's producing a mass or a tumor,
that would indicate a rhabdomyosarcoma.
And so, these are some important features
of rhabdomyosarcoma that we should be aware of.
The final disorder that we're going to talk about
is vaginal carcinoma.
Vaginal carcinoma is a carcinoma
that arises from the squamous epithelium
that lines the vaginal mucosa.
I've already told you that the entire vaginal mucosa
is lined by squamous epithelium.
This tumor is classically related to high-risk HPV,
so you're thinking about HPV 16, 18, 31, and 33.
And the precursor lesion for this is dysplasia,
which, again, is called the vaginal intraepithelial neoplasia,
also called the VAIN.
And that, again, is the dysplastic precursor
from high-risk HPV,
which eventually becomes vaginal carcinoma.
Now, one important thing to note
is that patients who get vaginal carcinoma
that eventually invades and spreads
will get spread to regional lymph nodes
as, again, carcinomas generally go to regional lymph nodes.
But what you need to know
and what's particularly high-yield here
is that because the vagina is derived
from two different sources,
depending on where the cancer is,
the spread will be to two different sets of lymph nodes.
So recall, again, that the vagina,
the lower one-third,
is derived from something called the urogenital sinus.
And so cancers that arise from the lower one-third
will actually spread to the inguinal nodes.
Recall, again, that the upper two-thirds of the vagina
is derived from the malarian duct.
And so cancers from the upper two-thirds
will actually spread to the regional iliac nodes.
And this is, again, particularly high-yield
because it's a nice way that examiners
can go back to basic anatomy
and test you on relationship of embryology
and basic anatomy to clinically relevant issues
related to cancer.
And that concludes the section on vagina.
Again, a lot of important principles
that are derived from some important tie-ins.
And hopefully you'll be able to paste all that together.